VINAY S BHARAMANAIKAR

Bengaluru, India (+91) 9740739113 | vbharamanaikar@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/vinaybharamanaikar/

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A Veteran with sound mid-level Managerial experience spanning over a decade in the field of Operations Management. A Cost-conscious and Communicative professional, familiar with Business Principles and Management of Operations, Vendors, Assets, Resources, Contracts, and moderately complex Projects. Additionally, experienced in Administration, Recruitment, and Competency Mapping of personnel and have managed high levels of Operations and Logistics in VUCA environment across multiple cross - functional domains.

EDUCATION

INDIAN INSTITUTE OF MANAGEMENT, INDORE Executive Programme - Business Management for Defence Officers	Indore, India Sep. 2021 – Mar. 2022
INDIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, DELHI Post Graduate Diploma – Naval Construction	New Delhi, India Jul. 2009 – Dec. 2010
VISVESVARAYA TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY, BELAGAVI Bachelor of Engineering – Mechanical Engineering	BELAGAVI, KARNATAKA Jun. 2004 – Jul. 2008

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE – INDIAN NAVY

NAVAL SELECTION CENTER KOLKATA, INDIA Position: Operations Manager and Competency Mapping Professional OCT. 2019-PRESENT

- Managed and developed customer service (operations related to transportation of candidates) in risky environment, by planning and controlling resource allocation to optimize the "operations service" to customer (candidates) which ensured safe transportation of over 10,000 candidates in time bound manner.
- Identified contractual inefficiencies and developed & optimised the contract and related processes, whilst adhering to regulatory guidelines, which resulted in reduction of financial liability by 60%.
- Involved in recruitment operations of officers for the Indian Armed Forces (7,500 candidates) by carrying out competency mapping as part of selection panel and achieved desirable congruency rate which improved the board results.

NAVAL HEADQUARTERS NEW DELHI, INDIA Position: Deputy Director (Aircraft Carrier Projects) – Naval Headquarters APR 2018-OCT, 2019

- Under the ambit of Indo-USA Joint Working Group Aircraft Carrier Technology Cooperation, planned and coordinated 03 Foreign & Indian delegations' visits/ meetings, by engaging various stakeholders and internal partners, which resulted in building knowledge database to facilitate decision making at a strategic level.
- Managed various stakeholders and internal partners and played an 'interface role' for deliberating on the Statement of Case for futuristic Indigenous Aircraft Carrier project worth INR 39,000 Crore for the Indian Navy.

HEADQUARTERS KARNATAKA NAVAL AREA

KARWAR, INDIA Position: Operations Manager & Consultant – Karnataka Naval Headquarters APR. 2016-APR 2018

- Managed moderately complex projects and logistics operations of ships by proactively anticipating requirements and through management of contracts, supply chain, liaison with vendors, thereby fulfilling the domain specific logistic requirement of 8 ships.
- Lead the technical teams for resolution of operational issues in collaboration with other agencies by focusing on issue correction & prevention through Quality Focus and Root Cause Analysis.
- Managed repairs & inspection operations in a time bound manner and ensured adherence to standard operating procedures (SOPs) by examining and reviewing procedures followed by the offices/ ships, thereby ensuring safety of all units under the Headquarters.

NAVAL SHIP REPAIR YARD

KARWAR, INDIA APR. 2014-APR 2016

Position: Deputy Manager (Operations & Projects) - Naval Ship Repair Yard

As Deputy Manager Operations, augmented processes/ capabilities, maximized productivity of Fabrication department by employing innovative techniques, application of technical skills, carried out regular ship repair operations for 8 warships and numerous visiting ships hence ensuring their safety and functionalities at sea.

- Managed a challenging workforce of 300 industrial workers of varying skill sets (Including 09 supervisors and 01 Technical advisor) through establishing deep relationships, strong interpersonal skills, mentoring, maintaining positive environment and ensured smooth conduct of operations without a single incident of 'Strike' or 'Tools Down'.
- Mentored/ coached and carried out performance evaluation and individual development of 300 industrial and ministerial staff. Trained and guided skilled workforce towards upgrading their skill set.
- Responsible for 08 ships refit projects (including the country's only Aircraft Carrier) and 02 retro fitment/ upgradation projects (Includes 01 strategic platform). Through inventory/ contract management skills, optimization of inhouse/ contracted resources, delivered results to user's satisfaction.
- As project manager carried out strengthening of deck plating through liaison with private firms, managing inhouse and contracted resources within critical timelines enabling retro fitment of strategic equipment onboard a Naval Vessel.

INDIAN NAVAL SHIP ADITYA

KARWAR, INDIA

Position: Operations Manager and Head of Department

MAR. 2013– APR 2014

- Efficiently managed cargo (fuel) loading/unloading operations using custom made cargo management tools, resources, and time management skills, thereby ensuring ship's safety at all times and enabled readiness of ship for operational deployment even at short notice.
- Foreseen probable breakdowns/ defects and ensured a defect free operational cycle by carrying out adequate preventive maintenance of ship's equipment and systems, thereby maintaining 100% efficiency of departmental equipment/ systems for a 40 days long overseas deployment even in harsh sea conditions.
- Overseen timely scheduled maintenance of ship systems maintaining close liaison with the repair yard and civilian contractors.
- Addressed challenging fabrication operations whilst at sea which involved risk assessment, demanded bold decision-making, using onboard crew and equipment to achieve dynamic objectives during military exercises at sea.

INSPECTIONS AND TRIALS AGENCY

PORT BLAIR, INDIA

Position: Deputy Manager (Trials and Inspections)

FEB. 2011-MAR 2013

- As designated authority for scheduled Trials and Inspections on ships and ship systems, carried out onboard Trials and Inspection along with addressing bottlenecks through problem solving skills, thereby ensuring safety and operational availability of over 10 ships to the satisfaction of the competent authority.
- Carried out critical analysis of critical defects onboard ships by coming up with innovative solutions to the problems, thereby enhancing operability of over 10 ships.
- Certified various repair processes for ships docked in dry docks for maintenance by using various equipment, tools, technical skills and taking numerous decisions to ensure timely repairs and undocking/docking procedures.

INDIAN NAVAL ACADEMY AND TRAINING INSTITUTES

Position: Trainee Officer

KERALA, INDIA AUG. 2008– Feb. 2011

• Joined Indian Naval Academy and was undergoing training at various training establishments and academic institutes.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Provided innovative solution for load testing of end fittings for Strategic Equipment. The solution has been adopted by the Board of Officers and is currently being used extensively by the user to their utmost satisfaction, since it proved to be a cost effective and technically sustainable solution.
- As the Parade Commander of the course, commanded the prestigious Passing-Out Parade at the Indian Naval Academy.
- Have been appointed the Orientation Course Captain of the 7th Naval Orientation Course for exemplary performance during training.

LANGUAGES

English (Advanced), Hindi (Intermediate), and Kannada (Basic)

SKILLS

- Operations, Project Management, Planning, Communication, Decision Making, Delegation
- Leadership, Competency Mapping, Interpersonal Relations, Military Experience, Risk Management, Agility, Command and Control
- Lean Six Sigma Green Belt (Pursuing)